A Guide to the Parkway Citizens Association Records, 1938-1991
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Parkway Citizens Association Records, 1938-1991
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 118
10 boxes.
Parkway Citizens Association
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of William Nolden of the Parkway Citizens Association, May 2001.
Scope and Content
Record Group 118 contains part of the history of the Parkway Citizens Association dating from before World War II until the last decade of the 20th Century. The association, first known as the Maywood-Woodmont Improvement League, and later as the Thrifton Village Improvement League, took its present name in 1943. This collection contains materials from 1938 to 1991. In most of the files the records are scattered, and contain a range of materials, such as correspondence, newsletters, agendas and minutes, committee reports, county notices and state materials. There are 14 photographic prints and one unprinted negative noted in the Box Listing.
Among the major concerns of the association during these years were: zoning, including development of the Hendry Tract; uses for the Woodmont School building; the redesign of Lorcom Lane; community improvement and security; airport traffic and noise; and the building of Route I-66. This collection presently measures 14 linear feet, and is open to future accessions.
Arrangement
Record Group 118 is arranged by subject and by year as far as possible. The first two boxes contain records of cooperative efforts with the Arlington County Civic Association. The notebooks in Series 15, listed by year, were originally in scrapbook form, and contain a large proportion of newspaper clippings. Oversize drawings and maps are listed at the end of the arrangement, are filed separately. There are 14 photographic prints and one unprinted negative noted in the arrangement.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Citizens' associations; Community organization.; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Arlington County Civic Federation (ACCF) issues
  - General - ACCF bylaws, officers, committees, newsletters, 1968-1990 (Box 1)
  - General - agendas, minutes, 1980-1990 (Box 1)
  - Airports - committee files, 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Airports - committee files, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Airports - committee files, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Transportation - airports, et al, committee files, 1981-1987 (Box 1)
  - Transportation - airports, et al, committee files, 1988 (1) (Box 1)
  - Transportation - airports, et al, committee files, 1988 (2) (Box 1)
  - Transportation - airports, et al, committee files, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
  - Transportation - airports, et al, committee files, 1990 (1) (Box 1)
  - Transportation - airports, et al, committee files, 1990 (2) (Box 1)
  - Transportation - general, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Residential traffic management (Co. Board ad hoc committee), 1981-1988 (Box 2)
  - Residential traffic management (Co. Board ad hoc committee), 1988 (1) (Box 2)
  - Residential traffic management (Co. Board ad hoc committee), 1988 (2) (Box 2)
  - ACCF community issues, misc., 1981-1991 (Box 2)
- Additional Airport Materials
  - Metro. Washington Airports Environmental Impact Statement Supplement, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Notice of Proposed Rulemaking, FAA draft, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Citizens for Abatement of Aircraft Noise (CAAN) papers, 1987 (Box 2)
  - Citizens for Abatement of Aircraft Noise (CAAN) papers, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Washington National Airport safety issues incl. scatter plan, 1988-1989 (Box 2)
  - Regional airport issues, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Regional airport issues, 1983-1991 (Box 3)
- Parkway Citizens Association (PCA) general interests
  - Community imporovement, 1984-1989 (Box 3)
  - Community Development Program, 1982-1985 (Box 3)
  - Neighborhood Conservation Program, 1978-1983 (Box 3)
  - Neighborhood Conservation Program, local and state materials, 1984-1987 (Box 3)
  - Neighborhood security, 1980-1989 (Box 3)
  - Control of Speeding in Residential Neighborhoods, report, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Real estate issues, Parkway brochure, 1980-1983 (Box 3)
  - Virginia Association of Neighborhoods materials, 1987-1990 (Box 3)
  - North Uhle Street berm design, 1986-1988 (Box 3)
  - Improving Local Government, report, 1981, advisory committee note, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Dover-Crystal Association startup, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Arlington County promotional materials and maps, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Court House Plaza Business Agreement and History, 1984 (Box 3)
  - Outstanding Volunteer Award to Bill Nolden, 1987 (Box 3)
  - ACCF and PCA letterheads (Box 3)
- Relocation of Fire Station #3
  - Advisory Committee, 1989 (1) (Box 3)
  - Advisory Committee, 1989 (2) (Box 4)
  - Advisory Committee, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  - Advisory Committee report, 1985 (Box 4)
  - Relocation Study, Fire Station #1 1985 (Box 4)
  - Arlington Co. Fire Department Annual Report, 1988 (Box 4)
- Roadway environment and traffic
  - George Washington Parkway Environmental Impact Statement & Summary, 1985 (Box 4)
  - George Washington Parkway, Potomac Overlook & Palisades reports, 1984-1991 (Box 4)
  - George Washington Parkway/Lorcom Lane traffic reports, 1984 (Box 4)
  - Projects (general), 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - I-66 issues, 1979-1982 (Box 4)
- The Hendry Tract
  - Background, 1984-1986 (includes 1963 map) (Box 5)
  - Preservation Plan for Fort C.F. Smith and the Hendry Tract with additional background, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Rezoning - community and county papers, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Rezoning - community and county papers, 1987 (Box 5)
  - Rezoning - community and county papers, 1987-1989 (Box 5)
  - Fort Smith Crescent Preliminary Site Plan - negative, October 1986 (filed separately) (Box 5)
- Ground Transporation
  - Landscaping, safety, street lights, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - Other neighborhood issues, 1980-1991 (Box 5)
  - Chamber of Commerce, on-street parking issue, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - Transportation planning, VDOT and local documents, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - Reviews of Master Thoroughfare and Transportation Plans, 1982, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Master Transportation Plan, related papers and news clippings, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Master Transportation Plan, agendas, comments, reports, 1986 (1) (Box 5)
  - Master Transportation Plan, agendas, comments, reports, 1986 (2) (Box 6)
- Recommended Master Transportation Plan, Arlington County
  - Part 1, 1985 (Box 6)
- Community Issues
  - Zoning, 1980-1982 (Box 6)
  - Zoning, 1984-1986 (Box 6)
  - Zoning, 1986-1987 (Box 6)
  - Zoning Ordinance Amendment Notice, June 1986 (Box 6)
  - Zoning - Commercial Districts Study, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Other community issues, 1978-1986 (Box 6)
  - Other community issues, 1987-1991 (Box 6)
  - Uses for Woodmont School building, 1981-1983 (Box 6)
  - Uses for Woodmont School building, 1983-1987 (Box 6)
- Lorcom Lane Redesign
  - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
  - Lorcom Lane Redesign Task Force files, 1980-1986 (Box 7)
  - Lorcom Lane Redesign Task Force files, 1986 (1) (Box 7)
  - Lorcom Lane Redesign Task Force files, 1986 (2) (Box 7)
  - Lorcom Lane Redesign Task Force files, 1987 (contact sheet, 14381) (1) (Box 7)
  - Lorcom Lane Redesign Task Force files, 1987 (2) (Box 7)
  - Lorcom Lane Redesign Task Force files, 1988 (1) (Box 7)
  - Lorcom Lane Redesign Task Force files, 1988 (2) (Box 7)
  - Lorcom Lane Redesign Task Force files, 1988-1989 (14382, color) (Box 7)
  - Lorcom Lane Redesign Task Force files, 1989 (Box 7)
  - Lorcom Lane Street Narrowing Test, 1989 (Box 8)
  - Lorcom Lane Redesign Task Force Report, 1989 (Box 8)
  - Lorcom Lane/Spout Run intersection, plans and land use map (n.d.) (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous Community Issues
  - Arlington County Annual Reports, 1985, 1986 (Box 8)
  - Site Plan Review Committee agenda, 1981 (Box 8)
  - Parks, recreation, beautification issues, 1981-1991 (Box 8)
  - County schools - newsletters, releases, correspondence, 1981-1991 (Box 8)
  - Newsletters, various subjects - Parkway and others, 1984-1990 (Box 8)
- Parkway Organization Files
  - Minutes, 1956-1965 (Box 8)
  - Minutes and administration, 1981-1984 (Box 8)
  - Minutes and administration, 1985 (Box 8)
  - Minutes and administration, 1986 (Box 8)
  - Minutes and administration, 1987-1992 (Box 8)
  - Newsletters, releases, agendas - County and community, 1991 (Box 8)
  - Constitution, bylaws, history, 1948-1974 (Box 8)
  - Meeting notices, membership lists, 1979-1982 (Box 8)
  - Treasurer's book, 1955-1958, 1972-1974, a few bank statements, 1981-1986 (Box 9)
  - Member accounts, 1946-1955 (Box 9)
  - Member accounts, 1976-1982 (record book) (Box 9)
  - Membership lists, 1984-1987, Post Office bulk mail instructions (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, various subjects, list of advisory groups, 1981-1991 (Box 9)
- County Notices
  - Arlington County Notices, Zoning, 1982-1987 (Box 9)
  - Arlington County Notices, Zoning, 1987 (Box 9)
  - Arlington County Notices, Zoning, including background info, 1987 (Box 9)
  - County notices, zoning and others, 1988 (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous Items
  - Newsletters, Center for Urban Education (CUE) and others, 1987-1990 (Box 9)
- Parkway Notebooks
  - 1938-1940 (Box 10)
  - 1941-1945 (Box 10)
  - 1946 (Box 10)
  - 1947 (Box 10)
  - 1948 (1) (Box 10)
  - 1948 (2) (Box 10)
  - 1949 (1) (Box 10)
  - 1949 (2) (Box 10)
  - 1950 (1) (Box 10)
  - 1950 (2) (Box 10)
  - 1951-1952 (1) (Box 10)
  - 1951-1952 (2) (Box 10)
  - 1953 (Box 10)
  - 1954 (Box 10)
  - 1955 (Box 10)
  - 1956 (Box 10)
  - 1957 (Box 10)
  - 1958 (Box 10)
  - 1959 (Box 10)
  - 1960 (Box 10)
  - 1961 (Box 10)
  - 1962 (Box 10)
  - 1963 (Box 10)
  - 1964 (Box 10)
  - 1965 (Box 10)
  - 1966 (Box 10)
  - 1967 (Box 10)
  - 1968 (Box 10)
  - 1969 (Box 10)
  - 1970 (Box 10)
  - 1971, Book One (Box 10)
  - 1971, Book Two (Box 10)
  - 1972, Book One (Box 10)
  - 1972, Book Two (Box 10)
  - 1973 (Box 10)
  - 1974, Book One (Box 10)
  - 1974, Book Two (Box 10)
  - 1975 (Box 10)
  - 1976 (Box 10)
  - 1977 (Box 10)
  - 1978 (Box 10)
  - 1979, Book One (Box 10)
  - 1979, Book Two (Box 10)
  - 1980, Book One (Box 10)
  - 1980, Book Two (Box 10)
  - 1981 (Box 10)
  - 1982 (Box 10)
  - 1983 (Box 10)
  - 1984 (Box 10)
  - 1985 (Box 10)
  - 1986 (Box 10)
  - 1987 (Box 10)
  - 1988 (Box 10)
  - 1989 (Box 10)
- Maps and drawings
  - Tube 1
    - Arlington County Civic Assocations, revised March 1996 (Othertype 1)
    - Fort Smith Crescent Preliminary Site Plan, October 1986 (Othertype 1)
  - Tube 2
    - Lorcom Lane Marking Plan, Plan A, (n.d.) (Othertype 2)
    - Lorcom Lane Marking Plan, Plan B, (n.d.) (Othertype 2)
  - Tube 3
    - Woodmont School and Surroundings, plat (n.d.) (2 copies) (Othertype 3)
    - Woodmont Center Preliminary Design, (n.d.) (Othertype 3)
  - Oversize Map Drawer 4
    - Potomac Crest Preliminary Site Plans, 4 sheets, March 1987 (Map-case 4)
    - Windy Run Nature Area Entrance, Plan, July 1961 (Map-case 4)